What do we have right here is GPT6
Astro, which is a new generation of
intelligence. And the president, Greg
Brockman of OpenAI, called this a
generational leap and said could
eventually be seen as the arrival of
artificial general intelligence or AGI.
Now, quick timeline because I think this
is pretty funny. September 1st, 1 p.m.,
we got Fable 5.1, and everyone's been
kind of freaking out. It's been all over
X and YouTube since it dropped. And then
two hours later at 3:30 p.m. on the same
day, OpenI made this tweet which said,
"As we prepare to release Astra, we're
focused on making increasingly capable
AI safe and broadly accessible." And
they put out this whole blog. It shows
some benchmarks about how much better
Astra is than 5.6 Soul, which is an
amazing model. I've been using codeex
with 5.6 Soul to honestly drive most of
my day-to-day. Anyways, let's go back to
this post. They dropped this video on X
today and they only dropped the first
like 12 seconds of it. Now, it's really
interesting because today, September
3rd, at 10 a.m., pretty much every AI
model went down. Claude, OpenAI, Grock,
Cursor, and right after these all went
down, that's when OpenAI and CHAGBT
dropped these two videos on X that
obviously blew up because everyone was
like, "Oh my gosh, Astra's coming
today." And this video right here that
they originally dropped was the
introduction. It was this first part of
this video right here.
>> Create a yellow circle there.
>> Done.
>> Okay, take this and make it look like a
rocket.
I like this video to take a lot more
detail.
>> Your yellow circle is now a window on a
rocket.
>> Okay, this is awesome. Now, make a 3D
model in
>> opening letter.
Let's build a
>> Anyways, if you guys want to watch the
rest of that video, you can obviously
get to it here at this page. But
anyways, what happened? We are
introducing GBT6 Astra, the world's most
intelligent and aligned model. This
model brings together years of research
and big bets across pre-training,
reinforcement learning, and alignment.
Astra was supposedly trained on over a
100,000 GPUs at Texas Stargate site
which is apparently the most amount of
training that has ever gone into a model
and it is rolling out today but only to
a limited set of organizations and I
think this is through their daybreak
program or maybe it's called Daybreak
Access but this will be not available to
us yet. It said it will be available to
us in the coming days to chatb plus pro
business and enterprise users and
through openi API and AWS. So absolutely
cannot wait to get my hands on that. But
the benchmarks here are insane how much
better this thing is apparently than
Claude Fable 5.1 and for cheaper on all
of these different benchmarks. It is
pretty ridiculous. Astra is our most
aligned model with substantial
improvements in understanding user
intent and model behavior. You can
delegate tasks with greater confidence
in Astra's judgment. As one way that we
test this, we built a new evaluation
informed by the hugging face incident
that evaluates whether a model facing
difficult or impossible task will go
beyond its intended scope. And compared
to GBG516 Soul, which without production
safeguards went beyond the authorized
target 48% of the time, Astra didn't do
this at all. So it seems to be much more
safe, meaning its intent to exploit is
much lower. It's also apparently the
famous browser use logo from OpenAI, the
world's best computer use model, which
is insane because GBZ 5.6 Soul is
already so so good at browser use and
computer use, but apparently it's a new
frontier here for computer use. This
screen spot pro benchmark, you can see
this is insanely high. It obviously is a
little bit more expensive than Soul
here, but it is scoring like a 92%. And
this is basically can the model locate
in a screenshot the right areas to click
or the right areas that it needs to
analyze or look at. And obviously it
scores much higher here than Soul as
well as Opus 5 and for much cheaper than
Opus 5. Now there are so many benchmarks
here that are insanely impressive.
They're blowing a bunch of other models
out of the water here with Astra. But of
course that's what every single release
blog of a model looks like. It always is
the best, the cheapest, the smartest,
the fastest, a new frontier, a new step
of intelligence. So, I just cannot wait
to get my hands dirty and actually put
it headto-head against Fable 5.1 and
against 5.6 Soul. But, I really think
the timeline on all this was really
funny, really interesting. These videos
dropped and then we saw inside of
Codeex, we saw the tags come through
GBD6 Astra and GBD6 Astra AON. And then
later today is where we saw this quote
come out with Greg Brockman and talking
about why this matters. And we saw a
bunch of different news articles and
things. Someone also said that GBT6
somehow has them more hype than GTA 6,
which I thought was kind of funny. We
see these two blog posts came out and
then they actually ended up being taken
away. So then if you went to that
address, you couldn't get there. Then we
saw these other benchmarks come out and
then we get this information about this
being released just to people inside of
the Daybreak Access program. Now, right
now it seems like the pricing is going
to be double that of 5.6 Soul. So
similar to where Fable 5.1 is. And is
this the model that puts them ahead of
Enthropic? That's what I can't wait to
find out because as of lately, I have
been using Codex more. Fable 5.1 now, of
course, I've been using that a lot. But
this model in the Codex harness, if it
truly is where the benchmarks show it
is, this might really start to like
skyrocket OpenAI and Codeex right back
to where they were kind of when you
think like 2023, 2024. Overall, I think
that this launch has been pretty weird.
like it feels like they always kind of
and by they I mean open eye and
anthropic they wait to just stack
updates and releases on top of each
other so that they kind of like own the
news and the media and YouTube and
everything but this one has just felt a
little bit odd to me. I don't know. I'm
really excited to see when we get it. It
says, you know, over the next coming
days. Hopefully we get that very very
soon. And I don't know. I think OpenAI
probably played this really well because
I think, you know, GBT6 is going to have
way more virality and hype around it
than I think Fable 5.1 will once this
thing drops. So, I'll keep you guys
updated obviously, but that's going to
do it. Appreciate you guys making it to
the end. I'll see you in the next one.